<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Pacquet-boat advice, or, A discourse concerning the war with France between some English gentlemen and a French-man betwixt Calis and Dover.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N399</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25502</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08999533</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08999533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1290:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Pacquet-boat advice, or, A discourse concerning the war with France between some English gentlemen and a French-man betwixt Calis and Dover.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Edwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Marchamont Nedham.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42172:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Pacquet-Boat Advice: OR A DISCOURSE Concerning the WAR WITH FRANCE, Between ſome Engliſh Gentlemen and a French-Man, betwixt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> and <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnis fabula fundatur in veritate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Edwin</hi> at the three <hi>Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-Street,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42172:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42172:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PACQUET-BOAT ADVICE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAVING received Advice from ſome of my Friends in <hi>England,</hi> that there was a little cloud of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ariſing by reaſon of the Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the growing greatneſs of the French, their many great and unexpected Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, which they ſeemed not only obſtinately reſolved to keep themſelves poſſeſſed of, but by the progreſs of their Arms to enlarge and extend; ran gueſſing that in all probability theſe ſtorms would not be allay'd without ſome ſhowers of Blood, I began to unfix my ſelf from my reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at <hi>Mompellier,</hi> whether my Curioſity and the Courſe of my Studies had carried me; and my intentions were to have ſpent ſome time, and then to have paſſed over the <hi>Alps</hi> to ſee <hi>Italy,</hi> the Garden of the World.</p>
            <p>But receiving Letters of freſh date, giving an account of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Marriage with the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> and His Majeſties calling of the Parliament, ſooner than the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral expectation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42172:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I began then to think that there was ſomething at the bottom of the flying Rumours: being not willing to run the hazard of being ill treated in <hi>France,</hi> where I had not ſo perfectly made my ſelf Maſter of the Language as to paſs for a Native, and conſidering, that I had no way to ſupport my ſelf but by Bills of Exchange or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, if there ſhould be a War between the two Nations, I began to reflect how difficult it would be for me to ſecure my ſelf of conſtant ſupplies, and that if I had them, poſſibly I might run the riſque of being ſuſpected and ſeiſed for an Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencer; and not daring to truſt to the Charity of a People who are ſo impoveriſhed, as generally rather to expect it from Strangers than to afford it them; and where my very being an Engliſh-man would deprive me of the Charity of ſuch as were able, ſince they would look upon me as an Enemy; and in truth fancying that I ſhould make a very ill Begger, it being a Trade I had no acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with, upon theſe conſiderations I thought it more adviſable to take my Leave of <hi>France,</hi> and to retire into my Native Country: upon which reſolution I departed with the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency that offer'd, for <hi>Paris,</hi> where when I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, the Rumor was hot amongſt the Engliſh, that there would be a War, and that very ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, though the French were very mute and huſh about it.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations, made me think of ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſs time then I intended at <hi>Paris,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I made immediately for <hi>Callis</hi> in order to my coming over in the Pacquet-Boat for <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42172:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
We went aboard with the morning tide, the day proving exceeding fair, and the wind which we had ſcarce enough, and not directly for us; it made our paſſage ſomething more tedious; but however the Company were ſo Civil to themſelves and one to another, as to endeavour to ſhorten the paſſage, by ſtealing ſome hours in entertaining themſelves with variety of diſcourſes upon ſundry ſubjects.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt there was one Gentleman who ſtarted the diſcourſe, concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Rumour of the War, and deſired the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Company about it, whether they did believe it would prove ſo in good earneſt, or whether it was not only an overture and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. His concern and inquiſitiveneſs made me guilty of the ſame humour, and rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe amongſt a great variety of Entertainment, all the Company had diſcovered themſelves, as to their deſigns and profeſſions, and ſome of them without any reſerve, even to their very Names, and the places of their habitation, yet I found this perſon not ſo innocent and ſimply li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral, only he told us he was a Merchant in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> who had ſome Correſpondents in <hi>England,</hi> and that the News of the War had perſwaded him to croſs over the Seas, and ſo for <hi>London,</hi> to endeavour to ſecure his effects there, in caſe there ſhould be a Rupture in good earneſt, and that he had conſiderable Bills of Exchange upon the account of ſeveral of the greateſt French Merchants in <hi>England,</hi> I gave him the patience of hearing, but I confeſs no great credit to his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42172:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
words; for me thought his Mine, his Equipage, and his Diſcourſe betrayed ſomething more in him, than meer Merchant; and I perceived he had been abroad upon other affairs than thoſe of Traffique, for he gave us a punctual account of the moſt conſiderable Actions of the preſent War in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany:</hi> but that which gave me the greateſt ſuſpicion, was his frequent mention of ſomething more than a bare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of moſt of the great Perſons of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and particularly of Mounſieur <hi>Lovois</hi> and Mounſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> whom he call'd the great Patron of Merchants, trade and induſtry, extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him to heaven, and proteſting that if his deſigns took effect, <hi>France</hi> would certainly be the only <hi>Emporium</hi> or Market of the World. This Jealouſie, that he did Trade with theſe great perſons only for Diamonds, having once infected my imagination, I had a curioſity to drive it as far as I could, with all the ſtudied Ignorance and ſimplicity I was capable of, and pretending great kindneſs to this Nation a folly too common and uſually true with the Engliſh, who are wont with a kind of Witchcraft to dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the French. So that we fell ſmartly upon the Subject of the War, and in regard I appear'd moſt forward in my Civility, and ready to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain his diſcourſe, he thought he had met with a right Engliſh Spaniel; and therefore making his application particularly to me Mounſieur (ſaith he) you are an Engliſhman, and though you have ſpent ſome time in <hi>France,</hi> yet I doubt not but by your appearance, which ſeems to diſcover
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42172:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you to be no common perſon, you have good intelligence from perſons of condition, you will infinitely oblige the Company and my ſelf in a moſt particular manner, if you will honour us with your opinion, whether or no you do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that we ſhall fall from thoſe good terms of Friendſhip and Alliance, which his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> has hitherto conſerved for his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Sir, replyed I, you ſet too obliging a value upon the opinion of a Stranger, but it is the uſual effect of your generoſity, which I ſhall in ſome meaſure indeavour to merit by my obedience to your commands: for I was willing to pay him with his own Coin. But Sir, added I, your queſtion is of too great conſideration, to find a reſolution from my private opinion. Affairs of that high nature are only tranſacted in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets of our great Maſters, and it may be it is no leſs a point of preſumption than folly, for us to concern our ſelves about them. <hi>Mounſieur</hi> (ſaid he briſkly) what we ſay is only to divert our paſſage, and borrow an hour or two from theſe ſlow Sails and the Wind, which uſes not at this time of the Year to be ſo ſluggiſh. But in my opinion there are ſeveral reaſons which may be alledged to perſwade the World, that this will not come to blows.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid a good blunt Gentleman with a Scar of honour in his face, who lay all along in the Boat, and had not ſpoken till then; it may be you are not ſo well acquainted with the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as I am; for my part I am not much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42172:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cern'd in affairs of State, nor am I acquainted with the Counſels of Princes, but let me aſſure you by what I have heard and know, that if it were put to the Vote of the People, whether a War or no War with <hi>FRANCE,</hi> I believe not one in a thouſand, but would be for a War.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur, ſaid the Frenchmam a little fired at his diſcourſe, no wonder at that, the people are like the Element which now carries us, full of flouds and ebbs, and it may be they will to morrow be as forward for a Peace as to day they are for a War; you Engliſh love to talk of Wars, but you hate to part with your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to deſray the charge of it.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid the Gentleman, raiſing himſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, I know not whether we can part with our money, but we will part with our blood freely, 'tis ſaid indeed you part with yours, and ſhoot golden Bullets, and make uſe of Keys of the ſame metal, which will open a breach or a Gate into the ſtrongeſt Fortifications; but Sir we have been uſed to do it with Steel and Iron, and yet give me leave to tell you, I hope we ſhall be ſo wiſe, rather to part with our money, than to keep it till the French comes with arm'd Troops to collect it, as they do in their own Country, and I hope, yet before I die to help to open ſome of the Gates of <hi>Paris</hi> with that hard metal, and to hear the drums beat the heavy Engliſh march through the Streets again, which once ſpoil'd a Jeſt of one of your Kings.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur, ſaid the French Merchant, as he call'd himſelf, biting the nails of his thumb, by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42172:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which I knew he was angry, <hi>Jerne Diabile,</hi> you will find ſomething to do before you come there; the King of <hi>FRANCE</hi> has two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>gens d'arms</hi> who will bid all <hi>Europe</hi> ſtand, and 100 Sale of Ships, who will ſpeak Thunder and Lightening, and make bold to ſtop your paſſage.</p>
            <p>Meſſires (interpoſed I, not willing to have theſe heats ſpoil our converſation) be ſo obliging not to tranſport your ſelves into a heat about an affair, which was only ſtarted, for our diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, there is no War yet, and I hope none there will be. Sir, anſwered the Engliſh Gentleman fiercely, there is not, but I hope there will be, and that quickly too. This Gentleman as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood after our Landing, was an Engliſh Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, a Souldier of fortune, who was taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner going wounded from <hi>Maeſtritcht,</hi> and not having wherewith to ranſome himſelf, according to the rate ſet upon him, had been a long time very ill uſed amongſt the French, but having made friends to procure a ſmall ranſome, which they were willing to take rather than none at all, having got his Liberty; was coming over to look for ſome imploy wherewith he might at once ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie both his neceſſity and revenge: I gave him a little ſign which he underſtood, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to hinder the proſecution of the diſcourſe he laid himſelf down again, upon which I took up the former argument of my French Merchant, and deſired him to favour us with the reaſons that moved him to believe there would be no War.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur (ſaid he) can the Engliſh Nation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42172:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
poſſibly live more happily than at preſent they do, whileſt enjoying peace they have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Traffique of the whole World, without paying any <hi>Gabels,</hi> Taxes, I think, you call them; and would it not be a ſtrange thing for them to put their finger into their Neighbours fire when there is no neceſſity; when they have all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, that he has all the Honour and Eſteem for them imaginable, and that he would be ready to do them all the good Offices, as his Majeſty did in the late War with <hi>Holland</hi> in 1665. when the Count <hi>D'Eſtrees</hi> was ſent with a Squadron of gallant Ships to your aſſiſtance againſt the Dutch.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur ſaid I, people ſpeak variouſly of that aſſiſtance, and I have heard ſome perſons affirm that Mounſieur <hi>D'Eſtrees</hi> did the Engliſh more prejudice, than kindneſs; and I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I ſaw a Letter, which affirmed that the not coming in of the French Squadron raviſh'd an aſſured victory from the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Upon which the Steerſman of the Veſſel would put in his oar into the Boat, marry ſaid he, I was then aboard the <hi>London</hi> under Sir <hi>John Harman;</hi> and I ſaw never a Ship of the French ſtrike a ſtroak, but how do you call him, Mounſieur <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> he fought like a gallant man board and board with the Dutch, but they ſay, when he came home he was clapt up in the Tower of <hi>Paris</hi> for his pains.</p>
            <p>Friend, ſaid I, to him, you mean Mounſieur <hi>Martel,</hi> and that he was made a priſoner in the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> but it was not for fighting, but for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying the order of his Admiral. Mounſieur
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42172:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
added the French Merchant, it was for ſome Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which he gave the Count <hi>D'Eſtrees,</hi> which did not become him to give, nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to receive, but what ſignifies one idle talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Captain, who was juſtly puniſhed for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence, but Mounſieur ſaid he, turning himſelf to me, if it were not the advantage of Trade, which you do and may enjoy upon keeping up a good underſtanding with the French, yet the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſence of his Arms, which is ſo glorious beyond all that ever were before him, attended with a thouſand victories, a thouſand ſucceſſes, might perſwade you not to be ſo haſty to enter into a war with a Nation, ſo great, ſo Potent, ſo For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and who is not without hopes ſtill of greater aſſiſtances and alliances; and poſſibly e're long you may hear that ſome other Princes have declared in favour of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir ſaid I to him, the Argument which you uſe to perſwade to peace is that which generally I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in <hi>England</hi> is accounted the greateſt motive of the War; the wealth and puiſſance, the Victories and Conqueſts of the French, is that which makes them look't upon as too great and dangerous a Neighbour both in Peace and War; in peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will certainly, they affirm, diminiſh their trade and treaſure as they find by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and in War, there is no doubt, but their greatneſs muſt needs make them ſenſible of their danger, and they eſteem it therefore a point of prudence to endeavour (if poſſible) to arreſt the courſe of their deſigns, before they break all the banks, and ancient limits, which were the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42172:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
boundaries of their Anceſtors, and overflowing theſe parts of the World with a dominion, the name of which is odious to the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur reparted the French Gent. you do well to put it onely by way of ſuppoſition (if poſſible) for I aſſure you, had you but ſeen the French Armies ſuch brave men, ſuch gallant Captains—</p>
            <p>Upon which the Engliſh Captain, who I thought had been at his repoſe ſtarts up; what men do you mean, pray Sir? Are you not obliged to our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men for your brave atchievements you talk of; pray who was it that took <hi>Maeſtritcht?</hi> Are you not obliged to the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> and the Engliſh for that Town? Who was it that ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Mareſchal Turene</hi> oftener than once in <hi>Alſace?</hi> and who was it that brought off his Army after that he was knockt o'th' head? when theſe men are drawn off from you, and when they come to fight againſt you, we ſhall hear of another Story.</p>
            <p>Sir ſaid I to him all the World muſt allow, that the French are brave men, well diſciplin'd, and that their Commanders are the moſt vigilent and expert Captains of the Age.</p>
            <p>Pray Sir, ſaid he ſhort upon me, are you an Engliſhman Frenchified, or a Frenchman in the diſguiſe of Engliſh? But be an Engliſh-man or a French-man, or what you will I would tell you a Story of one of the gallant French Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, which will be reaſon enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all Engliſhmen to love them leſs than they do (if it be poſſible) and to fight with them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42172:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and beat them too, which is very poſſible; for let them give you never ſo good words at preſent if ever you come within their clutches, they will uſe you like Dogs and worſe, for they will give you a knock but the Devil a bit with it. I was a Captain at <hi>Woerden</hi> when the French lay in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> and if you will give me leave I will tell you of a brave ſpeech which the Duke <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> now the Mareſchal <hi>Montmorency</hi> made to his Soldiers;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſieur</hi> ſaid the French Merchant, interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, pray ſpare the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I preſume you do not know him; for he is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the moſt obliging gallant Gentleman of the world.</p>
            <p>Sir, reply'd the Captain, he may be what he will; I have ſeen him, and if he were here I would ſay what I have ſaid; and hope as gallant as he is, if I can come near him for his life Guard to change a Piſtol with him loaden with a brace of ſlugs of good Engliſh Lead, and though mine will not ſhoot ſo far as your French Piſtols (which they ſay are better for Battery then heavy Cannon) yet they will kill the gallanteſt French-man in the Army, if they have but the luck to hit him three inches underneath his feather. And for the Duke <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I will juſtify.—</p>
            <p>Hold, hold; Noble Captain, ſaid I, you are a man of war, we are all peaceable, and I beg the favour of you, that you will allow us the freedome of diſcourſe, 'tis only to paſs away our time till we come to <hi>Dover,</hi> it will not now be long, and therefore applying my ſelf to my Merchant, Sir; ſaid I, there is no doubt but the French are a moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42172:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
potent Nation, and if ſome other Princes of the Empire ſhould joyn with him, it would be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable addition to his power; but ſtill give me leave to ſpeak in favour of my Country-men the Engliſh, they are a people not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; and if it be true, which is ſaid, that there is a ſtrict confederation between them and the Hollanders, they will out do you far at Sea; and if they cut of your Navy, they cut off an Arm from <hi>FRANCE,</hi> which one may ſay as the Turk comparing the loſs of the Battel of <hi>Lepanto</hi> to that of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> it is worſe cutting off the head than cutting off the hair, becauſe the one will grow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but the other never; and beſides the ſtopping of your Trade, and keeping your Wines and other Commodities upon your hands, will make your Money run upon the Lees, and is cutting the Nerves of War as mony is alwaies eſteemed. And as this Power at Sea may well Ballance all that you can ſay of your Maſters, ſo the Armies that <hi>ENGLAND</hi> may adde to thoſe of the Confederates at Land, will more than Ballance the aſſiſtance you promiſe your ſelf, and yet ſome perſons are of opinion, that the Princes will ſtill maintain their Neutrality till they ſee which way the dye of War will fall; you know it is ſafe joyning with the victor, and in the mean time, they keep their Country free from winter quarters and plunder: but beſides all this, his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> will now be at great liberty to aſſiſt the Confederates with thoſe brave men who made themſelves Maſters of the obſtinate Towne of <hi>Stetin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42172:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Mounſieur</hi> ſaid the French Merchant you ſpeak a great meaſure of reaſon, but we can difficultly perſwade our ſelves that you are in good earneſt, though ſome things have paſt of late that begin to ſtagger a great many people: yes ſayes the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who could hold out no longer, I believe it doth ſtagger a great many people, and the French eſpecially. But that, ſaid the Captain, for all your pretentions of being a Merchant, I believe you are one of his Agents, who with the Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change you told us of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are going into England to hold intelligence, and ſow jealouſies; that is a ſort of Merchandize which you have of late Trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with very much in all parts of the World: but it may be e're long we ſhall hear, that you are broke by the diſcovery of your Correſpondence. And I hope thoſe Engliſh people, thoſe dull Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, who you think you can cheat and out-wit at your pleaſure, will be ſo wiſe as to ſee your tricks and Arts, and to underſtand that the gold you are ſo liberal of to ſome of them, is onely to guild the chains you intend to put upon them all. I am ſatisfied, if they knew you, but half ſo well as I do, or had but ſeen your kindneſs to the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> after it had been wheedled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſurrender, they would have little reaſon to truſt to your kindneſs. <hi>Mounſieur</hi> ſaid the French-man what is all this to the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid the Captain, I think it is a fair warning to the Engliſh to ſtand upon their Guard, and to endeavour to put themſelves out of the danger of falling under the kindneſs of the French.</p>
            <p>Pray <hi>Mounſieur</hi> ſaid the French Merchant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42172:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(being a little cooled with the rough humour of the Captain) what are thoſe uſages which the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> complain of.</p>
            <p>Look you here ſaid the Captain, with that he pull'd a little book out of his Pocket, written in French intituled <hi>Advis fidele aux veritables Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>londois,</hi> all this is true and more then this I know to be true, when your gallant Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and the ſurintendant <hi>Robert</hi> had broken their Backs with Quarter, and Plunder, and Payments, and Confiſcations, and the Devil and all, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Lovois</hi> ſends them a Letter of Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a cup of Comfort, an Egg broken into a pale of Water, which you ſhall hear if you have pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meſſieurs, I'ay receu voſtre Lettre</hi> 23 <hi>du mois paſſe,</hi> &amp;c. but becauſe, Sir, ſaid he, you underſtand and ſpeak Engliſh ſo well as to make you paſs for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, if you can but leave your Shrug and your <hi>Jernies</hi> and <hi>Bongres,</hi> I will not trouble the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with a Language I do Love as little as it may be they underſtand, and therefore I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to teach the Marqueſs to ſpeak Engliſh, for he is a Civil obliging complaiſant perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meſſieurs,</hi> I have reciev'd your Letter of the 23 <hi>d.</hi> of the laſt paſt, by which I have ſeen all the reaſons which you repreſent, to make me under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the City and Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> are not in a condition to ſatisfie the Demands, which <hi>Mounſieur Robert</hi> hath made. I do eaſily Judge that you cannot do it without great trouble, but ſince neceſſity has no Law, and that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the King muſt be maintained, you ought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42172:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to accommodate your ſelves to the ſaid Sieur <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> ſo as to furniſh what he demands, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes it is impoſſible, but you muſt fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a moſt grand deſolation, and to mend the matter, the honeſt Sieur <hi>Robert</hi> tells them in ſhort, that ſince they made ſuch an impoſſibility to raiſe the mony demanded, he would cauſe fire to be ſet to the four quarters of the City, and he would light it in the middle himſelf, <hi>(a fin de reduire en Cendre une ville, qui u' eſtoit qui a charge &amp; inutile au Roy men Maiſtre)</hi> to the end I may reduce a City into aſhes which is unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and a charge to the King my Maſter. Is this true or not Sir.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur, ſaid the Frenchman, but what is all this to the Engliſh?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwered the Captain, I think it is a fair warning to the Engliſh to ſtand upon their guard, and to endeavour to put themſelves out of the danger of coming under the power of the French, and if poſſible, to put the French out of the power of putting them in danger.</p>
            <p>Why Sir, replyed the other, the French have no deſigns upon you, but onely as your own fears and apprehenſions perſwade you.</p>
            <p>What cryed the Captain, the French with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſigns? you ſhall as ſoon find a Monkey without tricks: From the Onyon Porridge-man to the Mareſchal you are all Politicians and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners. You have, you ſay, an hundred Sail of Ships, and two hundred thouſand Men, and you have no deſigns nor ever had I warrant you to make yourſelves Maſters of <hi>Flanders, Germany,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42172:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> at laſt. But by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Sir, you muſt paſs through fire as well as water before it comes to that.</p>
            <p>Well Mounſieur, ſaid the French-man, I hope for all this that there will be a Peace, and it may be I have ſome reaſon for my conjecture, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you we Merchants are in hopes, that you will not enter upon a War which muſt be ſo great a hazard and charge to the Nation. Sir, ſaid the Captain, you offer fair, but I cannot imagine why you ſhould be ſo troubled for the charge of the War, (tho, I hope it will come to your ſhare at laſt to defray it) unleſs you are afraid we ſhould ſo impoveriſh our ſelves by a War, that when you come to viſit us we ſhould not be worth the Plundring, and <hi>London</hi> would be good for nothing, but a ſecond Fire as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> ſaid of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht:</hi> and for my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and I hope all true Engliſh hearts are of the ſame tough old metal, you ſhall firſt try how you can digeſt our Steel and Iron before you taſte of our gold and ſilver.</p>
            <p>I found my two Gentlemen were running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a heat, and therefore I thought it better to make a tack (as the Boat then did) to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe, which we preſently did, and ſo paſt the time till we came to <hi>Dover</hi> Peer.</p>
            <p>As we parted the <hi>Mounſieur</hi> bid us adieu, and with the grace of a ſhrug particular to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he told me he ſhould be obliged infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he had the good fortune and honor to meet me upon the <hi>Exchange.</hi> Farewel ſaid the Captain, and have a care I do not meet you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42172:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſcattering your Bills of Exchange in the wrong place, and taking up News to ſend into <hi>France,</hi> in lieu of which you will return us ſuſpicious of your own making, to ſet us together by the ears at home, that ſo you may be ſecured from us broad.</p>
            <p>The French-man gave him a look full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and away he went to take poſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately for <hi>London,</hi> I was extreamly pleaſed with the rugged honeſt converſation of this Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and therefore deſired, if his affairs would permit, that we might be Companions for that night at <hi>Dover,</hi> where I had ſome little affair, he willingly conſented to my propoſition, and ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether we went to an Inn, where we had no ſooner taken a Room, but in come two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of my Relations, who had promiſed to meet me there, I was very much pleaſed at their arrival, and after mutual civilities paſs'd, and that we had like Engliſh men made ſome proviſion for Supper, without ever asking what we ſhould pay for it, and got a bottle of good Canary (for my Captain would drink no French Wine) we preſently fell to chat.</p>
            <p>The firſt queſtion you may be ſure was, What News? and the Captain was in great haſte, what ſhall we have a War with <hi>France.</hi> Sir, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of my Friends, Mens opinions are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as their Intereſts, but here is his Majeſties Speech, which it may be is news to you; and if you pleaſe to read it you may make your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture. Couſin ſaid I, you miſtake, if you think it news, or if in leſs than a weeks time we do
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42172:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not ſee in <hi>Paris</hi> every thing of moment that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at <hi>London:</hi> The French trade in <hi>Aleppo</hi> Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons; nay if we will believe them, they would perſwade us, that they can tell beforehand what will be done.</p>
            <p>That is an excellent way of intelligence ſaid the other Gentleman; but for my part I look upon it as a French artifice, and I am confident that that trick of pretending to know every thing amongſt us has done them conſiderable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for certainly it has given occaſion for thoſe jealouſies, which now break out amongſt us, as if there were a ſecret intreague betwixt the French and us, in order to ſome ſtrange deſign, and nothing will beat it out of ſome Peoples heads, but that this War is only for a colour. Sir ſaid the Captain here came over with us one of their Whiſperers, Piſtol-droppers, News-Makers, and away he is poſted for <hi>London</hi> to fill ſome peoples heads with Proclamations of Peace, Popery, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and others pockets with French money to ſwear it is true, they have Letters from <hi>France</hi> that confirm it.</p>
            <p>Couſin ſaid I, if the French can accompliſh this either way they have done their buſineſs. I aſſure you there is nothing they dread like a War with <hi>England.</hi> I ſaw it upon ſeveral poſts in <hi>Paris</hi> a ſevere Prohibition ſo much as to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch a War, but if they can drive it off with theſe reports, by diſuniting the King and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, they are lucky people and ſafe enough, and if they can make a Peace under hand, tho they give as much money for it as would almoſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42172:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
maintain the War, yet they have their aim.</p>
            <p>Well ſaid the Captain I doubt nothing, I am aſſured from a good hand, that before I get to <hi>London</hi> ſome reſolution will be taken. I told you ſome Stories of the French, but I have more of their pranks to acquaint the people with. Honeſt Captain and fellow Traveller, ſaid I, God ſend you good luck, I dare ſay you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow your Skill upon the French with a good will, but Couſin ſaid I, pray whats the matter. Sir, replied he they were wiſe that could tell you; and for my part I have little curioſity, and leſs acquaintance with State affairs, but ſome people I find are diſpleaſed: But prithee whats that to us, let us drink and be merry, and let the world go which way it will: By your favour Sir, ſaid the Captain, there are ſome people that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed becauſe they reſolved before hand to be ſo with every thing, but I preſume, that you and every Engliſhman are ſo far concern'd, that if you do not look about you, the French will e're long ſpoil both your Mirth and Drinking, what mean you (anſwer'd the other) I hope they will not ſpoil our Drinking, by Cutting our Throats, as they ſay the <hi>Danes</hi> did, which brought in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Pledging, or being Pledge when one drunk. Sir, ſaid the Captain, you may Live and Drink, and be Merry in that Hope, but for my part. I do not intend to truſt them. I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cut ſome of theirs fairly, for I hate to have my Weaſon ſlit, unleſs it be in the Field.</p>
            <p>Well, honeſt brave Captain, ſaid I, your ill u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42172:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
makes you in a rage againſt the French, and you think the Quarrel moves too ſlow, but, Sir, you muſt conſider, this is an Affair of great weight, and it is not good to make more haſte then ſpeed. Sir, ſaid he, the greater weight ſhould make the motion more quick; you do not ſeem to underſtand the worth of time, nor the briſk humour of the French, and therefore I have nothing to ſay to you, but I hope other People do and will conſider it. Come, come, ſay's my Couſin, what have we to do with theſe matters, it was never well ſince there were ſo many little States-men, and polit Polititians.</p>
            <p>I believe moſt people are ſatisfied of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a War, to reduce the World to the Old Ballance, and <hi>FRANCE</hi> amongſt the reſt, that ſo ſhe may be eaſie to her Neighbours, and they ſafe from her, and what would any body deſire more? 'Tis true there have been ſome Jealouſies, which have clogg'd the Wheels of this great Affair, but I can aſſure you, when I came out of Town, it was generally hoped that a little time would bring all people to a good underſtanding, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils to Unity, and the Affair to a happy Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid the Captain, this is a word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for I dare aſſure you, that the great hopes of <hi>FRANCE</hi> are grounded upon our Diviſions, which they are not ſo ill Huſbands, but they know how to improve, I heard one of them the other day ſay, that he thought that of the great Turk <hi>Solyman,</hi> might be applyed to the Engliſh, who will be of one mind (as he ſaid, the Chriſtian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42172:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Princes would) when all the fingers of his Hand were United into one.</p>
            <p>Come Captain, ſaid I, Unity, Secrecy, and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition added to our Courage, and Power, may do much, and I doubt not, but the neceſſity which ſeems to be upon us will make them all meet; the Cauſe is good for it is not for Soveraignity, but for Safety, not for Glory but Security, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Proteſtant Religion, our Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, from the Rapine and Ambition of the French, and he is no true Engliſhman who will not heartily venture his Life and Fortune, in ſuch a lawful War.</p>
            <p>Upon which, Supper came in, and we having talk'd our ſelves into a good opinion of eating, we gratifi'd our Pallates as well as the place would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and not long after every one retir'd to his Appartment, where I believe the Captain dream't of Drums, and Trumpets, and Cannons, and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado's Storms, and Battels, for he made a horrible noiſe in his ſleep lying in the next Room to me, for my part, like a perſon not much concern'd I ſlept, as heartily as the Souldier would permit me, who gave me ſeveral Alarms; and I can no more tell, what I dream't, then I can tell certainly what all men long ſo much to know, that we ſhall have a War with <hi>FRANCE,</hi> or ſuch a Peace as ſhall be Safe and Honourable for <hi>ENGLAND</hi> and all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
